[Music]
in an article entitled the treatment of
inoperable cancer
it was noted that 200 years ago it was
observed that a certain number of
malignant growths disappeared
after attack
of a type of strep infection and that
was 200 years before
1901 when this was published
a disproportionate number of cases of
spontaneous tumor regressions have
followed various infections
the thought is an infection maybe may
kind of so rile up the immune system the
cancer may get caught in the crossfire a
phenomenon that may have inspired
healers dating back to the ancient
egyptians thousands of years ago
but you don't know
until you put it to the test
though it wasn't formally studied until
the 1800s when doctors started
intentionally infecting cancer patients
the most famous proponent was william
cauley the so-called father of
immunotherapy at what would eventually
become memorial sloan kettering
he was convinced that having a severe
infection could cause cancer to regress
so with a great deal of courage he
started injecting cancer patients
the problem of course is that causing
infections is quite dangerous and two of
his patients died
however their tumors did shrink
if only there was a way we could boost
immune system without killing people
well that's the theory behind
therapeutic cancer vaccines one of which
has been in practice for decades
squirting a weakened bovine tuberculosis
bacteria into the bladders of patients
with bladder cancer to make the immune
system attack boosting long-term
survival up to 36 percent
okay but is there something we can eat
that can boost immune function
and my videos on countering
stress-induced immune suppression and
preventing common childhood infections
are viewed evidence about a type of
fiber in bakers brewers and nutritional
yeast called beta-glucans which are
considered
immunomodulatory compounds
suggested to enhance the defense against
infections and potentially
cancer
beta-glucans themselves do not appear to
have a direct cytotoxic effects in terms
of
killing cancer cells but may boost
anti-tumor immunity by activating our
immune cells for example if you take
freshly excised tumors of breast cancer
patients and let loose natural killer
cells upon them
they can kill off a small percentage of
the tumor cells but first prime them in
vitro with some yeast beta glucans and
they become five times more effective at
killing cancer cells
what if you just eat it though
when 23 women with metastatic breast
cancer were given just a sixteenth of a
teaspoon of nutritional yeast worth of
beta glucans they experienced a 50
increase in the number of monocyte white
blood cells in their bloodstream which
are part of our natural defenses as well
as a significant increase in their
activation
but it was just a two-week study the
clinical significance of this finding is
unclear
what we want to know is if they actually
live longer
the only english language randomized
double-blind placebo-controlled trial of
breast cancer patients and beta glucan
was more of a wound healing study where
they found that the women taking beta
glucan healed so much faster after
surgery
that the tubes could be removed from
their chests and armpits in some cases
days earlier
this was the first clinical study to
demonstrate improved wound healing using
oral beta glucans
the other two showing benefits for
pediatric burns and leg ulcers were
performed using topical beta glucan
preparations putting it on the skin
directly
something that did not appear to reverse
pre-cancerous skin lesions better than
placebo but that's because the placebo
cream works so well too
both groups showed a significant
reduction they speculated that since
each patient acted as their own control
putting the beta glucan cream on one arm
and the placebo cream on the other that
the application of beta glucans on one
arm may have been absorbed into the
system and helped on the other arm given
that substantive effects have been noted
following topical administration
but what effect might oral beta-glucans
have on the progression of internal
cancers
yeah oral yeast beta-glucans can cause
dramatic tumor shrinkage
in mice but there appears to be only one
human study published in english
20 patients with advanced cancer on
chemo were given a beta glucan
supplement in an open label uncontrolled
trial
60 of the patients supposedly reported a
sense of well-being while taking the
beta glucan and asked to remain on the
treatment after the completion of the
study
but that just sounds like classic
placebo effect
same thing with reporting being less
tired but this
is interesting one patient with lymphoma
and large lymph nodes in the neck who
delayed his standard chemotherapy for
four weeks during the study
noted a marked reduction in the size of
the nodes while taking the supplement
alone
so this you know
one
kind of anecdotal case is interesting
especially since there are no side
effects
but not exactly revolutionary
in japan there have been more than 20
randomized control trials on the use of
beta glucans as an adjunct cancer
treatment
which evidently show an enhancement of
chemo or radiation therapy resulting in
a positive effect on survival and
quality of life
for example there was evidently a study
on taking a yeast beta-glucan supplement
to help cancer relapse after surgery
there were no relapses in the treated
group compared about one in five in the
control group
even more intriguing yeast beta glucans
for inoperable cancer patients and stage
cancer
since only about one in 20 patients made
it three months and by six months they
were all dead
whereas in the treated group most
survived for more than three months not
one in 20 but most and 43 were still
alive
after six months now evidently it's not
clear how patients were divvied up into
treatment versus control groups if they
weren't randomly assigned they may have
inadvertently cherry-picked healthier
patients for the treatment group
which could explain the results now i've
looked for this study
everywhere so i could get it translated
but even the national library of
medicine couldn't find it if anyone out
there can though i'll do a follow-up
video
but the amount of beta glucan they used
is what you'd find in a single pinch
of nutritional yeast
which would cost less than a penny
and the only side effect would be
tastier popcorn
so why not give it a try
[Music]
foreign